Matter for that specific agency.
How they're kind of measuring progress, what outcomes they were going to achieve,
the costs of improving capability.
All of that stuff is
that you need for the public and for Parliament to understand what
progress is being made.
Yeah, I think that's a really key-
Needs to be.
Yeah.
I think that's a really key point actually, and this is something that this
committee's been grappling with, is
without having a really clear
reporting and
demonstrating exactly, A, why the
capability is important, what is actually being achieved with it, and
what the outcomes are. It's very difficult to track that, and
we've seen that in other areas. Without the actual
really robust reporting-
Yeah
... you can't see it. So
one of the things that would be really great to come out of
the committee's scrutiny would be, okay, we don't have that view right
now. We encourage the next committee to start asking for we
want to see that, and to be able to track it over terms.
And I think that's actually the key thing, because then an
agency, so agencies are able to understand and report on,
this is why it's important for us as an agency.
This is the outcomes that we're achieving, and this is how we're reporting on it.
And then it's able to be tracked and monitored, and I think that's the missing
piece a lot of the time.
And we also have our system lead agencies, Te Puni Kōkiri, Te
Kawa Mātaaho,
really lacking the information, such as through robust
public reporting, that they need to know,
hold agencies accountability accountable for their
progress just because the
quality of public reporting is generally-
Great, we'll come to you
... weak.
Oh, tena koe. Yeah. Yeah, ngā mihi ana.
Kia koutou and he rawe tō koutou aro ki
te whakapuāwai o te reo me ōna tikanga ki tō koutou
horopaki. Te
timaki o te mana aroha.
Metiria Turei.
Because of that, and I so appreciated your
report in terms of again and again and again, the focus
is on that.
Yeah.
I'm interested early on you have a focus
on the percentage of workforce who whakapapa Māori.
Mm-hmm.
Mm.
That doesn't come up much after that, and I read that as
because everything else that you are focused on isn't
actually dependent on or related to that. Can you just speak to that a bit?
Where does the...
So,
yeah, I agree. There was some early comments about capacity, I
guess, in terms of kai mahi Māori, percentage of kai mahi
Māori that are employed in the public service or
altogether and then in specific agencies.
I think there's definitely a link
between capability to engage with Māori and the
percentage of kai mahi Māori that you have in your
agency. But it was sort of outside of the scope of-
I appreciate. Is there, like,
first of all, is there, and secondly, should there be?
That's what I want to test.
I think there is when you think of
what kind of all the different attributes of what goes into
capability. So,
we saw it in quite a broad sense, but thinking
about individuals, it could be te reo, it might be
relationships,
just that you're really embedded in your local community.
It could be understanding
te ao Māori worldview, it could be values.
So the people we spoke to with kai mahi Māori and the public
service we spoke to didn't really want to pin it down on any
particular thing.
Right.
But I think kai mahi Māori are probably more
likely to have those existing relationships and that existing understanding
of worldview.
Do you-
I don't think it's-
Yeah
... it's not necessarily the case, but.
I just sometimes wonder whether, and this is why I'm wondering if you've
seen this at all in any of your assessment, as to whether there
is... Because I think that this, where I'm going now with this question, I think
this speaks to some of the oha and the raruraru
i te tino roto or
of the criticism that Willie was referencing
to, is this sense that in order to
pursue reo, tikanga, māramatanga
you need to have whakapapa. And I wonder,
whether it's possible in terms of the
encouragement and the instructions that you and then ultimately we are giving to
the public service, that we can
address that.
Sorry, I just need to understand the patai.
Is it
in terms
of
there's too much emphasis on only if
you whakapapa that you would be-
Yeah, that's what I'm trying to tease out. Yeah.
Because at the start of the report, you guys go where I would
predictively expect. So you're measuring those two things simultaneously,
so engagement with te ao Māori and whakapapa.
But then for the rest of your report, you just focus on the former.
As in you basically, and you're implicitly saying that what
really matters is your engagement with te ao Māori and the fullness
of māramatanga reo or tikanga. Yeah.
Yeah, go.
So-
On a really practical sense,
lots of our reports these days have
some information up front on a page that just talk to many things.
The main thing about the report, I would say, and our findings is
why capability matters for your organization.
So to touch on an earlier point,
before, if your organization doesn't have offices in the regions, okay,
is that a problem for you delivering the outcomes that you're wanting?
So why is it important? What roles
in your organizations are more important, have a greater effect on,
or would maybe benefit more from? And then again, it comes to monitoring,
reporting, and such like. So I think the report and our focus
would be on those things rather than whether or not your whakapapa-
Right. Okay
... I would say. Yeah.
I think, I wonder if
what you're trying to touch on is
capability in te reo or in te iwi
Māori
resting on those public servants that do whakapapa Māori-
Mm
... in an organization. I don't think it would be unfair to say
traditionally that has been the case.
If somebody needs to-
Yeah, we mentioned in there with the dial-in-
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. If somebody's going to do the karakia or if someone's going to do-
Right
... it falls to that small cohort of the
organization that, whakapapa Māori, and I think that traditionally has been
the case. And I think that can be, I'm going completely off the report
now, but I think that has been
a limitation in various parts where it shouldn't just
fall on that being a capability for-
Yeah
... as a kind of birth right capability.
But also,
does that stop the
encouragement or even
the confidence of non-Māori
in an organization to be able to step into that space?
And I think that we all need to
shake that off a little bit-
Yeah
... to have that. And I've
reflected personally in
my journey, I've met people and worked with people that whakapapa
Māori who
have sat beside me in a te reo class because they didn't
speak te reo, and they actually felt more whakapapa than I did
because-
Yeah
... of that very reason. And that was quite a
brain kind of like, wow, when I discovered that.
So I think you're on exactly the right track with that sort of questioning in terms
of how do we open up that space to
encourage and feel safe, I think.
And that
speaking te reo or just giving it a go is, or even
just stepping into that is a safe place to be.
And I think that's-
Members, the time is actually up, but I'm wanting to extend
this. I just want to check you don't have any meetings you have to rush off to or
anything?
No.
I'm all good, thank you.
I'd like to extend this a bit further because I think this is actually a valuable
conversation. Okay, so Steve.
Thank you.
So it sort of extends on the question of capability.
I've just sort of zeroed in on the section you did on corrections.
And one thing that strikes me is that as well as there being a
difference to those who are in the room who have existing
capability,
and it was sort of acknowledged in this thing that that
goes to a handful of people in corrections.
And that the importance of the relationships with
iwi from the rohe where and the corrections facility
was important.
But specifically around the Hōkai Rangi
outcomes,
one of the challenges you elucidate is that Correction
tracks its performance against high level outcomes such as re-offending
rates, but does not have a good way of measuring what difference its
investments in staff capability have in achieving those
outcomes. I wonder what the challenge and tension is there with
trying to
translate a deep,
potentially profound
opportunity for access for incarcerated people
to
learning of cultural history that they may not have
had access to previously.
And these
perhaps simplistic
other measuring tools like re-offending rates.
Mm.
You know what I mean? Like-
... are we trying to fit a round peg into a square
hole or vice versa with how the
value of fulfilling that treaty
obligation, in this instance, to recognize the
disproportionate number of Māori in corrections
and the acknowledgement that the Treaty of Waitangi tribunal made was that
Corrections was failing in its obligations to account for that.
That then that has to
be justified by
some sort of other measure of success and the value of
having high capability there.
I do agree with you. Sometimes things just add inherent
value to them.
Yeah.
I guess for Corrections,
when they're thinking about their high level outcomes, they need
to know and be able to measure what's actually working.
So if their goal is reducing
recidivism among Māori offenders-
Yeah
... they have to have a way of being able to measure for their own effectiveness.
Sure. I'm not saying you shouldn't measure for that.
Yeah.
It's useful to measure for that.
But is that the only test of
a fulfillment of a treaty obligation?
I don't think it's the only test, but I think that it's a-
I just can't see what the other tests are. Do you know what I mean?
It's not clear to me whether we're trying to
take a
difficult-to-measure positive impact and put it into
a simple, specific material outcome.
I think if we lift this up a little bit, just on this measuring bit, because
we have a lot of discussions
about the fact that, number one,
multiple governments, not just the government of the day, multiple governments with
Māori,
for you to attain more resources-
Mm
... you actually must have to prove that your systems work.
So measurability is really important.
And I think, personally, I believe there's a bigger emphasis on Māori outcomes in
achieving that than in a lot of other places in our government.
But that aside, that's number one.
But if we lift this up, I think we've got three very important
entities that which you have identified in the report, and that's the Public
Service Commission, Treasury, and TPK.
At that level there, I see that number one, the Public Service Commission,
they set
the incentive or not of the CEO-
Yeah
... of each organization as to how they perform.
If you do not have a KPI-
Mm
... on their books as to deliver Māori
outcomes. Dare I say it,
you won't have the emphasis required to get the change. That's number one.
Number two, Treasury. Measuring.
Mm.
Measuring dollar spends to Steve's point about how do
we actually truly
work out the outcomes are being attained-
Mm
... for the investment made of taxpayer dollar to help us get
even more investment where it works well and all that sort of stuff.
And number three, TPK.
There's a term used that they just don't have the teeth to be able to do their
job when they're trying to get alongside agencies, ministries, and all of that,
to help them be better than what they are in the Māori space.
So there's three prongs there, but it sort of comes back to what Steve's saying, is
that look at all these... It's a multi-pronged challenge that we've
got here, and I personally think it starts right at the top, as he has
set the mentality of the CEOs.
Mm-hmm.
But let's have a bit of a discussion about that.
Yeah. I think 100%. We've had many
discussions around
exactly those particular points.
Without the KPI, and it starts at the top
in terms of the chief executives, where
they're being held to account. And
if that's not set out at the very top, then it doesn't
have that trickle-down effect. You've also got
where is the reporting so you can say, "Okay, this is the pūtea that we're putting
here, and it's specifically linked to these particular
outcomes." Where is it being reported on?
And then you can see what's working well, what's
not working well. And even if it needs to come to a value for money
kind of conversation. If it comes down to the fiscal
conversation around not just that it's delivering on
outcomes, but it's delivering on what the money's being put
to be spent on.
And I think also it's that holding those particular central
agencies to account and Te Puni Kōkiri's in a
position where
everyone looks to them to be the ones to deliver.
But they're not the only ones doing it.
Ironically, they have a responsibility.
They have.
But they haven't got the tools.
Well, exactly that. And it's how they are standing alongside those central
agencies to be able to deliver on that and to have the teeth to go
back to your point on that.
Well, what about the idea of TPK having an
auditing ability of each agency,
ministry, to be able to present a report annually to this committee
or to the government about how they see them,
each part of our government actually.
I'm trying to find some accountability here-
Yeah
... for improvement.
Can I answer that, if possible? Yeah.
If you look at the recommendations, the way we've structured
them is to take consideration of how those players work.
So how our Public Service Commission,
TPK work together. So through our work,
the Public Service Commission were clear that TPK are the experts.
They hold the expertise. But as you've rightly pointed out, the public
service, they have the relationships with CAs, they have the KPIs, they
have the
stick, as it were. So when you look at the
recommendations in here, it's about TPK doing the right things to have a
view on whether or not the dial's been
moved, and that's through getting views from Māori communities and
from what they're seeing.
And I've got a framework that I'm putting out.
And giving that information to PSC so that they can
hold the agencies to account. So there's very much both of
them have to have quite a coordinated approach for it to work
effectively.
Yeah.
That's how I would see it.
I note that Dion Tuuta, our new CEO of TPK,
reviewed your report prior, which seems rather convenient.
Well, we didn't-
Of course, yeah.
Yeah. And I actually do wonder for the committee that we should make a
recommendation for the next committee because we'll be running out of time
ourselves, is to engage with TPK and particularly with Dion
and his experience with us here
to help us
find how we can actually move forward.
So that's potentially an area that we could focus on.
Yeah. And another, I spoke to one of my colleagues before I came over to see if he
had any other useful comments, and he reminded me that
Lindsey and himself are engaged with TPK on a six-weekly
basis about how they're going with the treaty settlements work.
Yeah.
Mm.
And that our follow-up to that piece of work will be happening in the new year.
The approach will be to be confirmed.
So again, if you have any thoughts around the nature of that work or where it
should go next, again-
Yeah
... through Lindsey, it would be a good time to feed into that.
Yeah, I did. Regular engagement with
TPK on various areas. And I know
that they would be welcoming of that regular engagement with the committee
and trying to really progress what they're trying to achieve.
We're on the same team here, basically.
Yeah.
I often say here at this committee, we're here to endeavor to get better Maori
outcomes, and this is what it's about.
And
I think that
when
just obviously thinking about coming here today and
looking at this report from the office as well as the Treaty Settlement Commitments
report, the advice we've given to you on the outcomes,
accountability settings and outcomes for Maori,
it's all inherently linked. The
recommendations and the
work that needs to be done to really drive
progress. That in all three of those areas, inherently, they
come down to the same things, which is system leaders
having that accountability and who essentially is accountable.
Where's the money going? Who's reporting on where the money's going?
And who's reporting on actually what's the results? What's the outcomes?
And that has to be consistent, and it can't be achieved just in
your term here around this table.
Right.
And so I think those things and those three points that you touched on, are
essentially those, and you can apply those across any of those
capability, treaty settlement commitments, ultimately
outcomes. It can be applied across the board, and it's
quite sensible metrics that people are asking for.
Accountability. Where's the money going?
Who's reporting on it, essentially, and how are we going?
And I think they seem quite basic, but being able to pull
that picture together seems to be quite difficult.
Yeah. I feel it's almost like we've got a book with multiple chapters, and
we are the editors for this point.
Yeah.
And the chapters are all mixed up. It's not a
readable book type thing.
Yeah.
And we're just trying to work all this out to get a
better hold from what we've got at the moment.
But hey, we are a little bit over time, and I appreciate that you're spending a bit
more time with us. And thanks to the members because
we do a lot of work at this committee, but if I was to bring it back to a focal
point, it probably comes to this. Is that what we're talking about here?
Everything that we talk about.
Mm.
And so this is so critical. I'm not saying it's easy to fix. It's clearly not.
It's multiple governments. It hasn't
achieved the
utopia, and we may never achieve it, but we can know we can be a darn sight better
than what we are at
the moment with regards to this.
And I think essentially that's what is
great around the
scrutiny
planning.
Yeah.
Because we don't want to keep trying to rewrite the book every single
term.
Yeah.
Trying to start the chapter again.
I think that's the legacy piece for the committees to, we've
identified these things, and we want you to
keep a focus on these particular-
So my last comment is that your office, you've written multiple
reports over the decades and all that.
Please keep it going because it's these type of reports that is the